Guide to the Louis Chevalier Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Louis Chevalier Papers
1940-1979
MS 1122
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20
(20 boxes)
Research notes, reference files, census documents, student papers on Paris, clippings, and photographs related to Chevalier's work on the history and demography of Paris. Included also are the manuscripts of two of his books: L'Assassinat de Paris and Montmartre du Plaisir et du Crime. The files also contain reference material used by Chevalier in his courses at the College de France. There is also a small amount of professional correspondence with Chevalier's American friends and colleagues.
Chevalier, Louis, 1911-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louis Chevalier, 1982.
Existence and Location of Copies
The original census sheets for selected streets in Paris, 1946 are available on microfilm (4,131 frames on 4 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM151.
Biographical / Historical
University professor and political scientist; born in Vendeé, France; educated at Ecole Normale Supérieure; professor College de France; professor Institut d'Etudes Politiques de Paris; former member Conseil supérieur de la Recherche Scientifique; former President du Conseil Scientifique du Centre Int. d'Etude des Problémes Humains de Monaco; former member Conseil Economique et Social du District de Paris; author of many books.
Scope and Contents
Research notes, reference files, census documents, student papers on Paris, clippings, and photographs related to Chevalier's work on the history and demography of Paris. Included also are the manuscripts of two of his books: L'Assassinat de Paris and Montmartre du Plaisir et du Crime. The files also contain reference material used by Chevalier in his courses at the College de France. There is also a small amount of professional correspondence with Chevalier's American friends and colleagues.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Portuguese -- France -- Paris; Europe; Paris (France) -- Census, 1946; Quartier Beaubourg (Paris, France); Quartier des Halles (Paris, France); Educators; Historians; Political scientists; Chevalier, Louis, 1911-2001
- Inventory, Circa 1940s-1970s
  Scope and Contents
  The Louis Chevalier Papers, the gift to Manuscripts and Archives of Professor Chevalier in 1982, consist of course material, research notes, reference files, student papers, clippings, photographs, manuscripts and correspondence relative to Chevalier's work on the history and demography of Paris. The files contain reference material for Chevalier's courses at the College de France as well as his books.
  The papers are roughly arranged in five subject categories established by Chevalier. The first category contains much research material on the ethnic make-up of Paris and on the history of immigration to the city. Files on immigrants from Brittany are particularly voluminous. A second category consists of files on the various sections and neighborhoods of Paris. Of particular importance in this category are two feet of 1946 household census forms for selected streets in Paris. Though the summary of the census has been published the rest of the raw data probably has been destroyed. (Because of the fragile nature of the forms this material has been microfilmed. Researchers will not be allowed to use the originals without first consulting the film.) The third and fourth categories consist of reference files organized by subject for two of Chevalier's recent books, L'Assassinat de Paris and Montmartre du Plaisir et du Crime respectively. The final category includes correspondence with Chevalier's American friends and colleagues.
  The material remains in very much the order Chevalier sent it with his notes of identification in place. No hardware has been removed and no preservation measures (except the microfilm) have been undertaken.
  - I
    - La caractère ethnique sous l'Ancien Regime: reference material notes, course material, student papers (Box 1)
    - La caractère ethnique, premier moitié du XIXe siecle: research notes, drafts (Box 1)
    - Immigration à Paris, 1850-1914: drafts, notes, reference material (Box 2)
    - Immigration à Paris à l'époque contemporaire (divers): reference material, printed matter, clippings, notes (Box 2)
    - Les Parisiens, caractère ethnique: notebook (Box 2)
    - Les Ethniques: reference files, course material (Box 3)
    - Les Espagnols à Paris: reference material, survey forms course material (Box 3)
    - Les Portugais: reference material (Box 3)
    - Les Bretons de Paris: reference material, student papers correspondence, clippings, notes (Box 4)
    - Les Bretons de Paris: reference material, correspondence, survey forms (Box 5)
    - Les Italiens à Paris: reference material, student paper (Box 5)
    - Les Nord-Africans à Paris: reference material (Box 5)
    - Caractère ethnique, 1960: reference material, notes (Box 6)
  - II
    - La ville et ses quartiers: course notes, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
    - Les quartiers: course notes, 1958-1959 (Box 6)
    - Le problème du quartiers: general data (Box 6)
    - Les quartiers(divers): reference material, course material, student papers (Box 6)
    - Les quartiers(divers): reference material, notes, student papers (Box 7)
    - Le Auvergnate de Paris: reference material, manuscript (Box 7)
    - Les Halles: reference material, clippings, maps (Box 7)
    - Les Halles: reference material, clippings, notes, correspondence (Box 8)
    - Divers "Halles" "Belleville": correspondence, books, printed material, student papers (Box 9)
    - Belleville: notes, reference material, clippings, student papers (Box 9)
    - Belleville: student paper (Box 10)
    - La Banlieue Nord: reference material, student papers, clippings, photographs, questionnaires (Box 10)
    - La Banlieue Nord: reference material (Box 11)
    - La Banlieue, leçons et documents: clippings, notes, background material (Box 11)
    - La Banlieue (District) [District de la région de Paris], 1968-1974 reference material, clippings (Box 11)
    - La Banlieue (District), 1968-74: clippings (Box 12)
    - 1958-1960: miscellaneous reference material dating earlier and going later than the dates specified by Chevalier; includes some material used in Les Parisiens. (Box 12)
    - Les Feuilles de Ménage du recensement de 1946: organized by street - la rue de Gravillers, la rue aux Ours, la rue Reunion, la rue St. Martin, la rue Bourg l'Abbe, Impasse Berthaud, la rue du Maure, la rue Quincampoix (Box 13)
    - Les Feuilles de Ménage du recensement de 1946: organized by street - la rue Quincampoix, la rue Michel le Conte, la rue de Granier St. Lazare, la rue Passage St. Avoyo, la rue Brantene, la rue de Vertus, la rue St. Martin, la rue Chapon, la rue Beaubourg (Box 14)
  - III
    - L'Assassinat de Paris: book manuscript, notes, reference material (Box 15)
    - Dossier 1 (Box 15)
    - Dossier 2 (Box 15)
    - Dossier 3 (Box 15)
    - Dossier 4 (Box 15)
    - Dossier 4 (Box 16)
    - Dossier 5 (Box 16)
    - Dossier 6 (Box 16)
    - Dossier 8 (no. 7) (Box 16)
  - IV
    - Montmartre du Plaisir et du Crime: book manuscript, notes, reference material (Box 17)
    - Dossier 1, Les premiers essais sur le livre, Introduction (Box 17)
    - Dossier 2, La premiere moitié du XIX siecle (Box 17)
    - Dossier 3, Le second empire et le commun (Box 17)
    - Dossier 3, Le second empire et le commun (Box 18)
    - Dossier 4, L'evenement (Box 18)
    - Dossier 5, 1890-1900 (Box 18)
    - Dossier 6, 1900-1914 (Box 18)
    - Dossier 6, 1900-1914 (Box 19)
    - Dossier 7, 1918-1929 (Box 19)
    - Dossier 8, 1930-1939 (Box 19)
    - Dossier 8, 1930-1939 (Box 20)
  - V
    - Montmartre, quartier place clichy: photographs (Box 20)
    - Correspondence du colleagues et amis americains: a selection (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous material found in the books sent by Chevalier (these books were given to Acquisitions) (Box 20)